Civil Rights History Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Interviews
  - Doris Adelaide Derby oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Atlanta, Georgia, April 26, 2011
    Summary: Doris Derby discusses her childhood in the Bronx, joining a National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) youth group, and attending Hunter College. She recalls her work in African art and dance, and traveling to Albany, Georgia, to join the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) with voter registration. She remembers teaching adult literacy in Mississippi with SNCC, starting the Free Southern Theater, and working for Head Start.
    - Moving Images, 8 video files of 8 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (111 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0008_mv01-08
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (46 pages); afc2010039_crhp0008_derby_transcript (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Jamila Jones oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Atlanta, Georgia, April 27, 2011
    Biographical History: Jamila Jones was born in 1944 in Montgomery, Alabama. She worked as singer and artist and wrote one of the verses of the song, We Shall Overcome.
    Summary: Jamila Jones recalls participating in the Montgomery Bus Boycott as a child and forming a singing group at age 11, the Montgomery Gospel Trio, to raise money for the Civil Rights Movement. She recalls helping the Freedom Riders, visiting the Highlander Folk Center, writing a new verse of the song We Shall Overcome, and founding the Harambee Singers.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (49 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0009_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (23 pages); afc2010039_crhp0009_jonesjamila_transcript (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Simeon Wright oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Chicago, Illinois, May 23, 2011
    Biographical History: Simeon Wright was born in 1942 in Doddsville, Mississippi. He married Annie Cole in 1971 and attended the Moody Bible Institute. He worked as a pipefitter, Sunday school teacher, and deacon. He is the author of Simeon's Story: An Eyewitness Account of the Kidnapping of Emmett Till (Chicago, IL.: Lawrence Hill Books, c2010).
    Summary: Simeon Wright discusses his cousin, Emmett Till, and his attempts to correct the historical record concerning Till's murder. He recalls Till's visit to his home in Mississippi, going to Bryant's store, and the night that Till was kidnapped. He remembers the trial, moving to Chicago, and how the murder and publicity affected his family.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (91 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0010_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (48 pages); afc2010039_crhp0010_wright_transcript (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Wheeler Parker oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Chicago, Illinois, May 23, 2011
    Biographical History: Wheeler Parker was born in 1939 in Schlater, Mississippi, grew up in Chicago, Illinois, and married Marvel McCain in 1967. He worked as a barber, photographer, and pastor. At age 16, he traveled from Chicago to Mississippi with his cousin Emmett Till and witnessed his kidnapping.
    Summary: Wheeler Parker, Jr., discusses his visit to Mississippi with his cousin, Emmett Till. He recalls the incident at Bryant's store and the night that Till was kidnapped, and Till's funeral in Chicago. He remembers how the murder and publicity affected his family, the reopening of the case in 2004, and efforts to memorialize Till.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files of 6 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (67 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0011_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (39 pages); afc2010039_crhp0011_parker_transcript (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Marilyn Luper Hildreth oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, May 24, 2011
    Biographical History: Marilyn Hildreth was born in 1947 in Oklahoma. Her mother, Clara Luper, was a teacher and local civil rights activist. Hildreth participated in many sit-ins and demonstrations with her mother and brother Calvin in Oklahoma City. She attended Douglass High School and worked in insurance sales and administration.
    Summary: Marilyn Hildreth describes growing up in segregated Oklahoma and the leadership of her mother, Clara Luper, in the local National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) youth group. She recalls participating in a drug store sit-in as a child, and the success the group had with several restaurants in Oklahoma City. She remembers her mother's leadership in the African American community in Oklahoma, and her involvement in the 1968 sanitation workers' strike.
    - Moving Images, 3 video files of 3 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (33 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0012_mv01-03
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (16 pages); afc2010039_crhp0012_hildreth_transcript (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Calvin Luper oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, May 24, 2011
    Biographical History: Calvin Luper was born in 1946 in Oklahoma. His mother, Clara Luper, was a teacher and local civil rights activist. He participated in many sit-ins and demonstrations with his mother and sister Marilyn in Oklahoma City. He attended Douglass High School and the University of Oklahoma and worked as an electrician.
    Summary: Calvin Luper remembers his mother, Clara Luper, and her leadership in Oklahoma City's National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Youth Council. He recalls participating in sit-ins in drug stores and restaurants, and hosting a radio show with his mother. He also remembers other leaders in Oklahoma's Civil Rights Movement, including Dr. Charles N. Atkins, E. Melvin Porter, and Ada Lois Sipuel.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (24 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0013_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (14 pages); afc2010039_crhp0013_luper_transcript (Box-folder 1/8)
  - James Oscar Jones oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Austin, Texas, May 25, 2011
    Biographical History: James Oscar Jones was born in 1943 in Willisville, Arkansas, married Mildred Neal in 1963 and had three children. He attended Pine Bluff A&M College, the University of Arkansas, and the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. He worked at the National Sharecroppers Fund, the Federation of Southern Cooperatives, Community Resource Group, and the Texas Department of Agriculture. He was a civil rights activist in Arkansas and member of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
    Summary: James Oscar Jones remembers growing up on a farm in Arkansas, the integration of Central High School in Little Rock, and attending the Arkansas Agricultural, Mechanical, and Normal College in Pine Bluff. He discusses his involvement in the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and meeting activists Bill Hansen and Ben Grinage. He recalls participating in sit-ins at Woolworth's drug store in Pine Bluff, and helping African Americans in rural areas become political candidates.
    - Moving Images, 8 video files of 8 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (127 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0014_mv01-08
    - Manuscripts, 2 transcripts (57 pages); afc2010039_crhp0014_jonesjames1_transcript; afc2010039_crhp0014_jonesjames2_transcript (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Anne Sobol and Richard Barry Sobol oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in New Orleans, Louisiana, May 26, 2011
    Biographical History: Anne Sobol was a lawyer and wife of Richard Sobol.
    Biographical History: Richard Sobol was born in 1937 in the Bronx, New York and married Anne Buxton in 1975. He attended Union College and Columbia University School of Law. He worked as civil rights attorney in New Orleans, Louisiana, and Washington, D.C.
    Summary: Richard Sobol discusses his early career as a lawyer in Washington, D. C., his involvement with the Lawyers Constitutional Defense Committee, and his decision to move to New Orleans to become a civil rights lawyer. He recalls meeting Robert Hicks of Bogalusa, Louisiana, being personally protected by the Deacons of Defense and Justice, and his involvement in many job discrimination cases brought against the Crown Zellerbach paper mill. He also discusses other employment, labor union, and housing discrimination cases he argued. His wife, Anne, is also briefly interviewed.
    - Moving Images, 8 video files of 8 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (121 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0015_mv01-08
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (59 pages); afc2010039_crhp0015_sobol_transcript (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Cynthia Baker Anderson and Fletcher Anderson oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Bogalusa, Louisiana, May 27, 2011
    Biographical History: Cynthia Baker Anderson grew up in Bogalusa, Louisiana. She was married to Fletcher Anderson and had three children.
    Biographical History: Fletcher Anderson was born in 1938 in Bogalusa, Louisiana, married Cynthia Baker and had three children. He graduated from Central Memorial High School and worked at the Crown Zellerbach paper mill in many jobs, eventually as an overhead crane operator. He joined the Deacons of Defense and Justice and the Bogalusa Voters League, and was a leader of the Civil Rights Movement in Bogalusa.
    Summary: Cynthia and Fletcher Anderson remember the segregation and job discrimination they faced in Bogalusa, Louisiana, and their decision to join the Civil Rights Movement. Fletcher recalls working many different jobs at the Crown Zellerbach paper mill, the harassment of the police and Ku Klux Klan, and joining the Deacons of Defense and Justice. They discuss their job discrimination lawsuits, their friends involved in the civil rights movement, and the current state of race relations in Bogalusa.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (82 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0016_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (39 pages); afc2010039_crhp0016_andersons_transcript (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Hicks family oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Bogalusa, Louisiana, May 27, 2011
    This interview is currently restricted.
    Biographical History: Barbara Maria Collins was born March 3, 1947 to Valeria and Robert Hicks with siblings Valeria Smith and Arlene Hicks. She attended Dillard University, BA and Tulane University, MPH.
    Biographical History: Carol Cummings Burras was born March 1, 1945 in Bogalusa, Louisiana, to Robert and Valeria Hicks. Her siblings were Gregory, Robert Jr., Charles and Barbara. She attended Our Lady of the Holy Cross, New Orleans, BA; and Southeastern University, MA.
    Biographical History: Charles Hicks was born February 25, 1945 in Bogalusa, Louisiana to Robert and Valeria Hicks with siblings Charles, Barbara Collins, Robert and Gregory. He attended Syracuse University, BA, MA and University of Maryland, MLS.
    Biographical History: Darryl Hicks was born in Bogalusa, Louisiana to Robert L. Hicks, Jr. He was the grandson of civil rights activists Robert and Valeria Hicks. He attended Southern University.
    Biographical History: Gregory Hicks was born June 1, 1950 in Bogalusa, Louisiana to Robert and Valeria Hicks with siblings Charles, Robert Jr., and Barbara Collins. He attended Southeast University, Lafayette.
    Biographical History: Robert Hicks was born November 15, 1948 in Bogalusa, Louisiana to Valeria and Robert Hicks. He attended Grambling State University.
    Biographical History: Valeria Payton Hicks was born in Bogalusa, Louisiana. She married Robert Hicks and had four children, Charles, Robert Lawrence, Gregory and Barbara Hicks Collins. She attended Picayune Community College for a Nursing degree and worked as a restaurant cook, domestic worker, and nurse.
    Summary: The Hicks family remembers their childhood in segregated Bogalusa, Louisiana, and their father, Robert Hicks, a local civil rights leader. They recall leading a children's civil rights march in Bogalusa to protest discrimination at Woolworth's, hosting two white civil rights workers, Bill Yates and Steve Miller, and being protected by the Deacons of Defense and Justice.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (154 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0017_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 2 transcripts (71 pages); afc2010039_crhp0017_hicks1_transcript; afc2010039_crhp0017_hicks2_transcript (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Geraldine Crawford Bennett, Toni Breaux, and Willie Elliot Jenkins oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Bogalusa, Louisiana, May 28, 2011
    Biographical History: Geraldine Bennett Crawford lived in Bogalusa, Louisiana, and worked as a maid and a nurse. She was the sister of civil rights activist Gayle Jenkins.
    Biographical History: Toni Breaux was born April 10 1947 in Bogalusa, Louisiana, to Gayle E. Expose, who later married Monroe Jenkins. Her siblings were Don Duan Expose and Willie "Chuck" Jenkins and she is the niece of Geraldine Bennett. She married Michael Harry Melton, Sr. in 1971 and Roger Breaux II in 1990 and had 3 sons. She attended Dillard University, BA; Southeastern Louisiana University, M.Ed. and worked as a teacher.
    Biographical History: Willie Elliot Jenkins was born December 7, 1952 to Gayle E. and Monroe Jenkins with siblings Willie "Toni" Expose and Don Duan Expose. He was the nephew of Geraldine Bennett. He participated in the Civil Rights Movement in Bogalusa, Louisiana, and integrated the public schools.
    Summary: Geraldine Crawford Bennett, Toni Breaux, and Willie Elliot Jenkins remember their mother and sister Gayle Jenkins, a leader of the civil rights movement in Bogalusa, Louisiana. They discuss their family history, how the family became involved in the movement, and Willie Jenkins' court case to integrate the public schools. They recall being protected by the Deacons of Defense and Justice, marching in local rallies, and memories of their late brother Don, who was also involved in the movement.
    - Moving Images, 8 video files of 8 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (82 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0018_mv01-08
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (57 pages); afc2010039_crhp0018_jenkins_transcript (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Annie Pearl Avery oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Selma, Alabama, May 31, 2011
    Biographical History: Annie Pearl Avery was born in 1943 in Birmingham, Alabama and grew up in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. She married Harrison Avery, had two children, and worked as a dishwasher in the 1960s. Avery was a civil rights activist and member of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
    Summary: Annie Pearl Avery remembers her childhood in Birmingham, Alabama, and Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, and joining the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) at age sixteen. She recalls attending a SNCC meeting in Atlanta and being stranded and threatened in Marietta, Georgia, on the way home. She discusses her involvement in the Albany Movement, her many arrests for protesting, marching with William Moore, and participating in voter registration drives in many locations across the South.
    - Moving Images, 7 video files of 7 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (91 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0019_mv01-07
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (45 pages); afc2010039_crhp0019_avery_transcript (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Gwendolyn M. Patton oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Montgomery, Alabama, June 1, 2011
    Biographical History: Gwendolyn Patton was born 1943 in Detroit, Michigan. She attended Tuskegee University, Antioch College, Union Graduate School, and Interdenominational Institute of Theology. Patton was a civil rights activist and archivist.
    Summary: Gwendolyn Patton discusses attending the Tuskegee Institute, where she became involved in many civil rights organizations and was elected student body president. She recalls hosting the Freedom Riders in 1961, and spending a year in a segregated sanitarium when she had tuberculosis. She recounts organizing Tuskegee students for the Selma to Montgomery March, occupying the Dexter Avenue Baptist Church, and registering voters in Lowndes County.
    - Moving Images, 8 video files of 8 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (111 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0020_mv01-08
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (50 pages); afc2010039_crhp0020_patton_transcript (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Charles F. McDew oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Albany, Georgia, June 4, 2011
    Biographical History: Charles McDew was born in 1938 in Massillon, Ohio. He attended Roosevelt University and South Carolina State University, and worked as a community organizer and educator at Metropolitan State University in Minnesota.
    Summary: Charles McDew recalls growing up in Massillon, Ohio, his family's involvement in the steel mill unions and attending South Carolina State University. He remembers being arrested three times in two days for not obeying segregation laws in South Carolina, founding the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), and registering voters in Mississippi.
    - Moving Images, 5 video files of 5 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (82 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0021_mv01-05
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (27 pages); afc2010039_crhp0021_mcdew_transcript (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Charles Melvin Sherrod oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Albany, Georgia, June 4, 2011
    Biographical History: Charles Sherrod was born in 1937 in Surry, Virginia, married Shirley Miller Sherrod in 1966 and had two children. He attended Virginia Union University and Union Theological Seminary, and worked as a community organizer and chaplain.
    Summary: Charles Sherrod recalls how he became involved in the Albany Movement in Georgia, recruited local residents, and led marches and protests against segregation.
    - Moving Images, 2 video files of 2 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (20 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0022_mv01-02
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (8 pages); afc2010039_crhp0022_sherrodcharles_transcript (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Joseph Echols Lowery oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Atlanta, Georgia, June 6, 2011
    Biographical History: Joseph Lowery was born in 1921 in Huntsville, Alabama, married Evelyn Gibson in 1950, and had three children. He attended Paine College, Paine Theological Seminary, and Chicago Ecumenical Seminary. He worked as pastor and civil rights activist in Mobile, Alabama, and was a co-founder of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC).
    Summary: Joseph Lowery recalls his position as pastor at the Warren Street Church in Mobile, Alabama, in the 1950s. He remembers joining the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), the differences in race relations between Mobile and other southern cities, and helping to found the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC). He reflects on the effectiveness of nonviolence, the libel suit against him, sit-ins across the country, and the Selma to Montgomery March.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (63 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0023_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (26 pages); afc2010039_crhp0023_lowery_transcript (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Matthew J. Perry oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Columbia, South Carolina, June 7, 2011
    Biographical History: Matthew J. Perry was born in 1921 in Columbia, South Carolina, married Hallie Bacote, and had one son. He attended South Carolina State College and South Carolina State College of Law, and worked as a civil rights attorney and judge in South Carolina. Perry died in 2011.
    Summary: Judge Matthew J. Perry recalls serving in the military during World War II, and experiencing discrimination during the war. He remembers watching a trial that inspired him to go to the newly formed law school at South Carolina State College. He discusses his start as a trial lawyer in Spartanburg, South Carolina, the famous civil rights cases he argued, joining the NAACP Legal Defense Fund, and his admiration for the African American lawyers who mentored him.
    - Moving Images, 3 video files of 3 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (55 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0024_mv01-03
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (23 pages); afc2010039_crhp0024_perry_transcript (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Ernest Adolphus Finney oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Columbia, South Carolina, June 8, 2011
    Biographical History: Ernest Finney was born in 1931 in Smithfield, Virginia, married Frances Davenport, and had three children. He attended Claflin College and South Carolina State University School of Law. He worked as a civil rights lawyer, judge and interim president of South Carolina State University.
    Summary: Ernest Finney recalls his father's teaching career and attending law school at South Carolina State College. He remembers defending the "Friendship Nine," a group of college students who protested segregation in Rock Hill, South Carolina. He discusses joining the South Carolina Human Rights Commission, serving as a state representative, and his election to the State Supreme Court.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files of 6 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (55 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0025_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (27 pages); afc2010039_crhp0025_finney_transcript (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Cecil J. Williams oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Orangeburg, South Carolina, June 9, 2011
    Biographical History: Cecil J. Williams was born in 1937 in Orangeburg, South Carolina, and married Constance Goode in 1959. He attended South Carolina State College and Claflin College, and worked as a photographer.
    Summary: Cecil J. Williams remembers his childhood in Orangeburg, South Carolina, and starting his career as a photographer for several African American publications in his teens. He remembers photographing President Kennedy, Thurgood Marshall, and other civil rights leaders. He also discusses the Briggs v. Elliot school desegregation case, and his photographs of the Orangeburg Massacre.
    - Moving Images, 5 video files of 5 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (117 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0026_mv01-05
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (58 pages); afc2010039_crhp0026_williamsc_transcript (Box-folder 2/8)
  - William Saunders oral history interview conducted by Kieran Walsh Taylor in Charleston, South Carolina, June 9, 2011
    Biographical History: William Saunders was born 1935 in New York, New York, married Henrietta Jenkins, and had 10 children. He attended Southern Business College, Southern Illinois University Vocational Education, and the University of Nevada. He worked as a politician and CEO of Committee on Better Racial Assurance Human Services Agency.
    Summary: William Saunders remembers his childhood on Johns Island, South Carolina, and working with Esau Jenkins, a local civil rights leader. He recalls serving in the army during the Korean War, attending the Highlander Folk School, and working at a mattress factory. He also discusses founding the Lowcountry Newsletter, helping the workers in the Charleston Hospital Strike of 1969, and running unsuccessfully for the state senate.